Today's דף Daf is
מ"ו. Mem Vav. We start at the bottom of מ"ה עמוד ב.
Mem Hey Amud Bet.
Two dots: הלחם מעכבת הכבשים. Halechem ma'akevet hakevasim.
So moving into, as we said, the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem discussion,
so at least it's somewhat topical. We have the idea that this
is at the end of this פרק. perek. We're now back to
קרבנות. korbanot. Which things are not מעכב זה את זה, ma'akev zeh
et zeh, but in the while we're talking about what's not מעכב,
ma'akev, also talking about some exceptions or some sub-things that are מעכב.
ma'akev. And the bread and the two lambs, not the big קרבן
korban that came with the bread, which was the one cow, two
rams, seven sheep, but the קרבן korban of the two lambs that's
mentioned there in אמור, Emor, which are the כבשי עצרת, Kivsei Atzeret,
which are שלמים, Shlomim, שלמי ציבור. Shlomei Tzibur. They come with the
bread. The תורה Torah says that they're waved with the bread. There
it says that one is מעכב ma'akev the other, but the question
is in which direction. Debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי
שמעון בן ננס. Rabbi Shimon ben Nannas. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
that if you have the bread alone, you can bring it, but
you don't bring the lambs alone; the lambs are only for the
sake of the bread. Ben Nannas says the reverse. If you have
the lambs alone, you bring them, but if you have the bread
alone, you do not bring it. So let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. הלחם מעכבת הכבשים. Halechem ma'akevet hakevasim. So this is
רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva's position. Without the bread, you don't bring the
lambs. מאי טעמא דרבי עקיבא? Mai ta'ama de'Rabbi Akiva? What's the reasoning
of רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? We're again about twenty lines from the
bottom, two dots. גמר "יהיו" מ"תהיינה". Gamar "Yihyu" mi-"Tihiyena". Because the פסוק,
pasuk, again, we're assuming that every time the תורה Torah says יהיו
Yihyu or some word like that, it means that it's מעכב. ma'akev.
And the תורה Torah here says by the two lambs, it says
יהיו. Yihyu. Oh, wait.
I think by here I have a חומש Chumash right here.
Okay,
so it says in אמור, Emor,
קדש יהיו לה' לכהן. Kodesh yihyu l'Hashem lakohen. Thank you. So that's
what it says by the lambs and the שתי הלחם. Shtei Halechem.
So there's some assumption, which is a little interesting why that assumption
is, that the יהיו Yihyu is not referring to both components; it's
only referring to one of those components, right? So let me just
read it: והקרבתם על הלחם שבעת כבשים תמימים,
Vehikravtem al halechem shivat
kevasim temimim, etc., etc. And then it says, ושני כבשים בני שנה
לזבח שלמים והניף הכהן אותם על לחם הבכורים תנופה לפני ה' על
שני
הכבשים. Ushnei kevasim bnei shana lezeva'ach shlomim vehinnif hakohen otam al lechem
habikkurim tenupha lifnei Hashem al shnei hakevasim. So that particularly associates the
bread with the שתי כבשים. shtei kevasim. קדש יהיו לה' לכהן. Kodesh
yihyu l'Hashem lakohen. So for some reason, there's an assumption that the
יהיו Yihyu is not going on both components, only on one. So
which one of those two components is the יהיו Yihyu must always
be present? So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva learns it out from the
תהיינה tihiyena exactly of a מנחה. mincha. חמץ תאפינה
סלת תהיינה. Chametz te'afena solet tihiyena. Excuse me, not the
מנחה, mincha,
the עומר. Omer. It says by the עומר, Omer,
right?
Hold on.
I'm sorry, I'm sorry. Not the עומר. Omer. Excuse me, right here
by the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem itself. It says earlier in the
פסוק, pasuk, ממושבתיכם תביאו לחם תנופה שתים שני עשרנים סלת תהיינה חמץ
תאפינה בכורים לה'. Mimoshvoteichem tavi'u lechem tenupha shtayim shnei esronim solet tihiyena
chametz te'afena bikkurim l'Hashem. Right, sorry. Because this is חמץ. chametz. The
עומר Omer is מצה. matzah. All right, so right here it says
יהיו Yihyu later when it's talking about both the bread and the
two lambs, and it said earlier תהיינה tihiyena when it was talking
just about the bread component of it. So therefore, רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says that we only say that the only thing that's מעכב
ma'akev is the bread.
Okay, why wouldn't both of them be מעכב? ma'akev? It says יהיו
Yihyu and תהיינה; tihiyena; it's close enough.
I know, but the גמרא... Gemara... well, it doesn't... well, we don't
have a יהיו Yihyu that clearly indicates that it's going by the
lamb part. Here it says יהיו Yihyu by the two of them,
and there it says
תהיינה. tihiyena. So we're... for whatever reason, we're assuming that the יהיו
Yihyu is referring to only one of the two components. Why we're
assuming that is not clear. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva learns it
from the תהיינה tihiyena it said earlier by the שתי הלחם Shtei
Halechem itself.
So, מה להלן לחם אף כאן לחם. Mah lahalan lechem af kan
lechem. So the same way over there it's bread, here too it's
referring to the bread component that that is what is מעכב. ma'akev.
ובן ננס, U-Ben Nannas, and בן ננס Ben Nannas who says that
the one thing that is מעכב ma'akev is the lambs, גמר "יהיו"
"יהיו". Gamar "Yihyu" "Yihyu". He learned it out from a יהיו Yihyu
where it says... רש"י Rashi quotes the פסוק, pasuk, hold on.
רש"י Rashi says by שבעה כבשים יהיו עולה לה'. shiva kevasim yihyu
ola l'Hashem. It said earlier by the animal part of the קרבן,
korban, not by the two lambs particularly, but by the large group
of animals: שבעת כבשים תמימים בני שנה פר בן בקר אחד ואילים
שנים יהיו עולה לה'. shivat kevasim temimim bnei shana par ben bakar
echad ve-eylim shnayim yihyu ola l'Hashem. Okay, so earlier in that פרשה
parsha it used the word תהיינה tihiyena by the שתי הלחם Shtei
Halechem and used the יהיו Yihyu by the animals part of the
big animal sacrifice, not the שתי כבשים, shtei kevasim, but the big
animal sacrifice. So בן ננס Ben Nannas is saying that יהיו Yihyu
tells me here, when it comes to the bread and the two
lambs, the עיקר ikkar is the lamb. יהיו יהיו. Yihyu yihyu. מה
להלן כבשים אף כאן כבשים. Mah lahalan kevasim af kan kevasim. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says,
ובן ננס נמי נילף מ"תהיינה"? U-Ben Nannas nami nilef mi-"tihiyena"? Why does
he not learn out from תהיינה? tihiyena? תוספות Tosafot says it's a
little strange, obviously the words are a little different, but it's indicating
that רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, at least, you know, there you're directly
linking the bread component to the bread mentioned earlier. You're linking the
שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem to an earlier פסוק pasuk about the שתי
הלחם. Shtei Halechem. So why doesn't he learn that out? מה להלן
לחם אף כאן לחם. Mah lehallan lechem af kan lechem. גמרא Gemara
says no,
דנין יהיו מיהיו ואין דנין יהיו מתהיינה. danin yihyu mi-yihyu ve-ein danin
yihyu mi-tehiyena. No, we'd rather learn it out from a word that's
exactly the same rather than תהיינה tehiyena that's not exactly the same.
And then the גמרא Gemara classically says, מאי נפקא מינה? mai nafka
mina? Why are you so limited? התנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, ha-tanna de-vei
Rabbi Yishmael, תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל tanna de-vei Rabbi Yishmael we taught,
ושפלו כעיניו בא הכהן, ve-shaflo ke-einav ba ha-kohen, these פסוקים pesukim by
צרעת tzara'at we quote this a lot to say that גזירה שווה
gezeira shava don't have to be exact. זהו שיבה זהו ביאה, Zehu
shiva zehu bia, returning is the same as coming. So therefore you're
allowed to learn גזירה שווה gezeira shava even if the words are
not the same at all, even if just their sense is the
same, the meaning is the same. So גזירה שווה gezeira shava doesn't
have to be exact. גמרא Gemara says, alright, הני מילי היכא דליכא
דדמי ליה. hani milei heicha de-lika de-dami lei. That's when there's nothing
that's exactly the same, so we can learn out even from something
that's roughly the same. אבל היכא דאיכא דדמי ליה, aval heicha de-ika
de-dami lei, when there's a word that's exactly the same or more
similar, מדדמי ליה ילפינן. mi-de-dami lei yafinan. We'd rather learn out from
the word that's the same or more similar. So Rabbi Akiva says
you have this פסוק pasuk that refers to the שתי הלחם shtei
ha-lechem and the lambs and it says יהיו, yihyu, which we're understanding
meaning that one of those components must be that way, is מעכב,
me-akeiv, you can't do it without it. And because earlier it says
יהיו yihyu by the... by the שתי הלחם, shtei ha-lechem, that's what
Rabbi Akiva says. Now Ben Nannes, what makes him focus on the
lambs? So the גמרא Gemara says like this, רבי עקיבא נמי נילף
יהיו מיהיו... Rabbi Akiva nami neilaf yihyu mi-yihyu... where are we? Yeah,
רבי עקיבא נמי נילף יהיו מיהיו. Rabbi Akiva nami neilaf yihyu mi-yihyu.
I'm sorry, so we now we know why Ben Nannes did not...
I'm sorry, I said it wrong. That's why Ben Nannes focuses on
the... on the... Did I say it right? Okay, Ben Nannes goes
to the... he does the יהיו מיהיו... yihyu mi-yihyu... one
second. בן ננס נמי... Ben Nannes nami... right. Alright, we said why
Ben Nannes does not go by the תהיינה tehiyena of the bread.
Wait a minute, hold on, Ben Nannes... wait, hold on, hold on,
I know why I'm confused right now. Ben Nannes says that earlier
it
says... I... right, okay, got it. Okay, so Ben Nannes learns out
the יהיו יהיו yihyu yihyu because that's what it says by the
קרבן korban component earlier, by the rams and the cows and the
sheep and so on. That's why he'd rather learn out that it's
the קרבן korban that's the עיקר ikkar and the word יהיו yihyu
is the exact same. Now why does Rabbi Akiva go back to
the bread? רבי עקיבא נמי נילף יהיו מיהיו? Rabbi Akiva nami neilaf
yihyu mi-yihyu? Why doesn't he learn out from the יהיו yihyu that's
referring to the קרבן korban component? Why does he go back to
the יהיו yihyu of the bread? Why does he go back to
the תהיינה tehiyena of the bread? Thank you. דנין דבר שמתנה לכהן
מדבר שמתנה לכהן ולאפוקי הני דעולות נינהו. danin davar she-matanah la-kohen mi-davar
she-matanah la-kohen le-afukei hani de-olot ninhu. Because if you have the word
by... it says by the bread and the כבשים, kvasim, you are...
that they should be... what does it say there? It says קדש
יהיו להשם לכהן. kodesh yihyu la-Shem la-kohen. So we'd rather say that
that is... and we have to learn it out, so we learn
it out either from bread or from the עולה. olah. Well, that's
the עולה, olah, we'd rather learn it out
in this פסוק pasuk that's talking about the bread and the כבשים,
kvasim, both of them a component goes to the כהן. kohen. The
כהן kohen eats the bread and the כבשים kvasim are שלמים, shlamim,
the כהן kohen eats the שלמים. shlamim. So here you have by
this combination of the bread and the שלמים, shlamim, they both go
to the כהן. kohen. Now we have to choose, which are we
going to link this to? Are we going to link it back
to the reference of the bread itself, which also goes to the
כהן, kohen, it's the same bread? Or are we going to link
it to the פסוק pasuk about the עולות olot that come with
it? Well, the עולות olot don't go to... only go to God,
don't go to the כהן. kohen. So if we're going to have
to link a יהיו yihyu to one of the earlier פסוקים, pesukim,
we'd rather link it to a פסוק pasuk that is similar to
this that goes to the כהן kohen and not to the עולה,
olah, יהיו עולות להשם yihyu olot la-Shem that only goes to God.
Okay, so that's why he learns it out from earlier. דבר כמתנה
לכהן מדבר שמתנה לכהן לאפוקי הני davar ke-matana la-kohen mi-davar she-matanah la-kohen
le-afukei hani to exclude the other category that comes with it, the
one, two, and seven דעולות נינהו de-olot ninhu that are עולות. olot.
Okay, so that's how we have this debate based on it. Now
of course it doesn't sound that way, you know, from the משנה.
mishna. The משנה mishna sounded like it was a much less of
a technical question of יהיו yihyu and תהיינה tehiyena and sounded like
it was much more of a conceptual issue of what do you
think is the עיקר, ikkar, how can... can the bread be brought
without the lambs and so on. But the גמרא Gemara here is
making it that very technical question of the יהיו. yihyu. ואיבעית אימא
בקרא גופיה קמיפלגי. ve-iba'is eima bi-kra gufei kamifligi. Or you could say
they debate the פסוק pasuk itself. קדש יהיו להשם לכהן, kodesh yihyu
la-Shem la-kohen, there's the פסוק pasuk that's referring to the bread and
the כבשים. kvasim. רבי עקיבא סבר, Rabbi Akiva savar, so he says
look it says יהיו להשם לכהן. yihyu la-Shem la-kohen. איזהו דבר שכולו
לכהן? eizehu davar she-kulo la-kohen? So it goes to the כהן. kohen.
Which thing goes of these two goes to the כהן kohen fully?
הוי אומר זה לחם, hevei omer ze lechem, the bread. Why do
the שלמים shlamim not go fully to the כהן? kohen? Because אימורין
סלקי אגב מזבח, eimurim salki agav mizbe'ach, the blood, the אימורין. eimurim.
So if it says קדש יהיו להשם לכהן, kodesh yihyu la-Shem la-kohen,
so the יהיו yihyu is referring to that of the... those... that
component of the two that is fully to the כהן, kohen, the
bread. ובן ננס, u-Ben Nannes, בן ננס Ben Nannes says, wait a
minute, מי כתיב קדש יהיו לכהן? mi ksiv kodesh yihyu la-kohen? It
doesn't say it's קדש kodesh to the כהן. kohen. There's another word
there. קדש יהיו להשם לכהן כתיב. kodesh yihyu la-Shem la-kohen ksiv. So
it's actually brings better my way, says בן ננס. Ben Nannes. איזהו
דבר שמקצתו להשם ומקצתו לכהן? eizehu davar she-miktzaso la-Shem u-miktzaso la-kohen?
What thing goes partly to God and partly to the כהן? kohen?
הוי אומר אלו כבשים, hevei omer elu kvasim, those are the lambs.
So I'm going to read קדש יהיו להשם לכהן kodesh yihyu la-Shem
la-kohen as referring... as emphasizing the lambs. ורבי עקיבא, ve-Rabbi Akiva, רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, מי כתיב קדש יהיו להשם ולכהן? mi ksiv
kodesh yihyu la-Shem ve-la-kohen? It doesn't say it goes to God and
to the
כהן. kohen. To God and from God it continues on to the
Cohen. So what does that mean? כתיב Ktiv כרב הונא k'Rav Huna
like רב הונא Rav Huna says דאמר רב הונא קנאה השם ונתנה
לכהן. D'amar Rav Huna kna'ah Hashem unetana lakohen. God acquired it and
gave it to the Cohen. And this is a general principle of
כהנים משלחן גבוה זכו Kohanim mishulchan gavoah zachu that when the כהנים
Kohanim are eating the קרבנות, Korbanos, it's very different from when they're
eating תרומה. Terumah. When they're eating תרומה, Terumah, it's like I'm just
giving it straight to the Cohen. A קרבן, Korban, the idea is
I'm giving it to God, and then God says, "Oh, what are
we going to do with this? Well we'll have the כהנים Kohanim
eat it," which is also conceptually linked to the idea of כהנים
אוכלים ובעלים מתכפרים, Kohanim ochlin u'be'alim miskaprim, that the אכילה achila of
the כהן Kohen in some ways is similar to the אכילה achila
of the מזבח mizbe'ach and is part of the ritual that achieves
the כפרה. kapara. So therefore they are getting it through God, not
directly being given to them. So says Rabbi Akiva, קודש יהיה לה'
לכהן—I'm Kodesh yihyeh l'Hashem lakohen sorry, yes, קודש יהיה לה' לכהן Kodesh
yihyeh l'Hashem lakohen doesn't mean God gets a piece of it, holds
on to a piece of it. It means it goes to God
but from God it passes on fully to the Cohen, and that's
referring to the שתי הלחם, Shtei Halechem, but it's not something that
God holds on to a piece of, and therefore he says it's
referring to the שתי הלחם. Shtei Halechem. So at the end of
the day the גמרא, Gemara, whether it's based on יהיו yihyu and
תהיינה, tiyenah, whether it's based on קודש יהיה, Kodesh yihyeh, still makes
it a question about the technical read of the פסוק, pasuk, that
they read the word יהיו yihyu to say one of these things
is עיקר, ikar, and then how do we read that, do we
read it's referring to the bread or is it referring to the
lambs? Again, in the משנה Mishna it didn't sound that way. In
the משנה Mishna it sounded more like it was a conceptual issue
that on the one hand Rabbi Akiva says let's face it, this
is a קרבן Korban about the bread, so the bread is really
what matters. And that בן ננס, Ben Nanas, although in the end
he tried to bring his proof from במדבר, Bamidbar, but certainly the
way the גמרא Gemara explained it—the משנה Mishna explained it at the
end of the משנה, Mishna, which is the תנא Tanna רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, is that it's about the fact that you can't bring
something without a קרבן, Korban, without an act of הקרבה. hakrava. So
you can't bring the bread without the lambs because what do you
do? There's no קומץ, komitz, there's no anything, so you need the
lambs to bring the bread. So that seemed to be the way
the משנה Mishna was focusing the debate, but the גמרא Gemara here
makes it a little more technical. Okay, so now we continue. Now
we're going to try to get an exact handle on the parameters
of the debate. So let's take a look. Last line on מ"ה
עמוד ב'. mem-hei amud bet.
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, so says Rabbi Yochanan, הכל מודים
שאם הוזקקו זה לזה שמעכבין זה את זה. Hakol modim she'im huzkeku
zeh lazeh shema'akvin zeh et zeh. If they became connected one to
the other, then they hold each other back. There's a certain moment,
which we're going to say in a minute what that is, where
they wave them, they שוחט, shocht, where at a certain moment you
say this is the package. And once the package has been defined
as a unit, then you cannot—then if you're missing a piece of
the package the whole thing is no longer good. Similar to what
רש"י Rashi said before, where רש"י Rashi said although you don't need
every קרבן Korban of the מוסף, Musaf, if you had all of
like seven lambs and then you lost one, then it's not a
good מוסף. Musaf. That once you have the whole thing, that defines
the whole thing as the package. So that's what Rabbi Yochanan says.
Once they are linked to one another, they become a package that
if they're missing one the whole thing is no longer good. And
the question is what is going to effect that link? ואיזהו זיקה
שלהם, V'eizehu zika shelahem, what is that connection, that linking that occurs?
שחיטה. Shchita. When you שוחט shocht the lambs, and we are going
to see this is going to be a classic assumption in the
גמרא, Gemara, question of even Rabbi Akiva agrees to this, that the
שחיטה shchita of the lambs מקדש mekadesh the לחם. lechem. Okay,
and the לחם lechem until you שוחט shocht the lambs has a
קדושת דמים, kedushas damim, it's owned by the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
not a קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. The difference being if they take
it outside it doesn't become invalid and so on. The bread gets
the קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf when the lambs get slaughtered, which again
shows the point at the end of the משנה Mishna of רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that you need some act of הקרבה hakrava so
that there's some significance to the bread. So when the lambs get
slaughtered and the bread becomes sanctified, so at that moment it becomes
one unit, one קרבן, Korban, and here at that stage everybody would
agree that if any piece is missing, it's no longer good. What
does this suggest? Two brief things about this. Number one is an
interesting thing about the word זיקה, zika, which we're going to see
a lot now for several pages. If anybody's learned יבמות, Yevamos, the
word זיקה zika appears all the time. And it's interesting because זיקה
zika is this generic concept which means a link, a connection, being
somewhat bound to one another. And so by יבמות Yevamos the whole
idea is that
the brother died, and now there's a זיקה zika between the brother
and the sister-in-law because there's some quasi-marital connection through the dead brother,
which then manifests itself fully as marriage if the act of יבום
yibum is done. So there it's referred to this זיקה, zika, this
connection. Here it's also זיקה, zika, same word, obviously applied in a
very different context, that links these things together as one type of
a unit. Now the other interesting thing here is the assumption that
שחיטה shchita matters for Rabbi Akiva. Rabbi Akiva remembers the one that
says you can bring the bread without the lambs. So he might
have said that even when you bring the lambs, they act somewhat
independently. But the גמרא, Gemara, and it will see it even more
clearly on the
עמוד ב', amud bet, does not—wants to assume that Rabbi Akiva doesn't
stay that far with the general idea that the שחיטה shchita of
the lambs is מקדש mikdash. *mikadesh* the לחם lechem. *lechem*. If you
don't have lambs and you bring the bread by itself, then fine,
it operates by itself. And there will even be a discussion in
the גמרא gemara *Gemara*, are you allowed to eat it? What do
you do with the bread? How do you bring it? Okay, but
that's like okay, that's an exception, and he allows for the bread
to operate by itself. But when it comes with the lambs, even
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* will admit that the primary way
of הקרבה hakrava *hakrava* is through the slaughtering of the lambs and
the sprinkling of the blood. So when it comes together, it works
together with the lambs, and therefore says רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* that
when the lambs are נשחטו *nishchtu*, now you've got a very defined
unit and now if the lambs go missing, the blood of the
lambs goes missing, or the bread goes missing, you have to, you
can't use any part of the קרבן korban *korban*. The whole thing
has to get, you know, disposed.
It doesn't mean that it's present at the same time though. You
don't do שחיטה shechito *shechita* of the bread obviously.
Right, but you do שחיטה shechita *shechita* when you have the bread
present.
Exactly, I mean in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash*.
In the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, right, presumably not in a פסול
Psul *psul* status, like if it was טמא tamei, *tamei*, it would
not be true, right, then you wouldn't. But if it's כשר Kasher,
*kasher* and it's in the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. Now the interesting
question is, let's say it's not in the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*,
but the פסול Psul *psul* of יוצא yotze *yotzei* by the לחם
Lechem *lechem* by the bread here
does not apply out of the עזרה *Azarah* because the bread is
a, can be eaten in all of ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*.
So, or the לחמי תודה Toda. *lachmei todah* can be eaten in
all of ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim*. The bread of, yeah, the bread of
the שתי הלחם Shtei ha-Lechem. *shtei halechem*,
yeah, pretty sure. Well, let me think because the lambs for the
lambs are שלמי ציבור Shalmei Tzibur *shalmei tzibur* which are קדשי קדשים
*kodshei kodashim* which can only be eaten in the מקדש Mikdash, *Mikdash*.
So is the same true about the שתי הלחם Shtei ha-Lechem *shtei
halechem*? I don't, I'll check in a second because it's true by
a תודה Toda *todah*, יוצא Yotzei *yotzei* by a תודה Toda *todah*
was only when the bread goes out of the what do you
call it, out of ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim*.
See, I'm sure the answer is like in an explicit משנה Mishna
*mishnah* later on here in מנחות *Menachot*. It's been so while since
I learned it so I'll have to remember here where the bread
can be eaten. But just hold on one second, let me see
if I can quickly find it.
שתי הלחם Shtei ha-Lechem. *shtei halechem*... no, it's telling me
what's מעכב meakev, *me'akev*.
Yeah, what were we saying?
No, what we're saying is it's interesting that even רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* puts it at שחיטה shechita *shechita* because you might
say that you know at least maybe the sprinkling of the blood
or or even, well the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to try to push it even earlier.
Yeah, or no, I was going to say that the שחיטה shechita
*shechita* is מקדש Mikdash *mekadesh*, so I would have thought it to
be later because you know you don't even bring the two together
until we do the תנופה tenufo, *tnufa*. I would have thought once
you do the תנופה tenufo. *tnufa* then if something happens to it
afterwards.
Well, you know the תנופה tnufa *tnufa* is before the שחיטה shechita
*shechita*.
Oh okay, then I would have said that the,
well that's what the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is going to ask is
about the תנופה tnufa *tnufa*. Okay, I'm going to have to look
this, this is a good question because the שלמי *shalmei* the what
do you call it the
כבשים kvasim *kevasim* are קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim* and they don't go
outside the מקדש *Mikdash*.
So in terms of this here let me give it one more
second see if I can find it.
Anyway, I would have thought after the תנופה tnufa *tnufa*. Right, well
that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to go. But we
have a principle that the שחיטה shechita, *shechita* is מקדש *mekadesh* so
that's clearly what the, okay I'm going to have to look this
up, okay, but about where the bread is actually eaten of the
שתי הלחם Shtei ha-Lechem, *shtei halechem*. I'm sure it's like a מפורש
משנה mishnah, *meforash mishnah* somewhere.
Alright, so let's take, let's go on. Okay, so yes, the bread
has to be there, it has to be in the right place,
it can't be, it can't be טמא Tamei? *tamei*, and then you
שחט shachted *shachat* it then it all gets defined as one unit.
So let's take a look. אמר עולא *Amar Ulla*, so עולא *Ulla*
said. באו במערבא *Ba'u be'ma'arava*, they asked in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*.
תנופה tnufa עושה זיקה osah zika, או אינה עושה זיקה oseh zika.
*tnufa osa zika o eina osa zika*. So it's similar to Mike's
question. You do the waving of the two together, of the bread
and the lambs before you שחט shachted. *shachat*. So maybe that's enough
to define it as a unit. So פשט לה מדרבי יוחנן *pashat
la mi-derabbi Yochanan*, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said, well why don't
you just infer it from you know what רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*
is saying? דאמר רבי יוחנן שחיטה עושה זיקה Shechitah Oseh Zikah, *de'amar
rabbi Yochanan shechita osa zika*. Since רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says the
שחיטה shechita *shechita* makes it as one unit, מכלל דתנופה אינה עושה
זיקה oseh zika. *miklal detnupha eina osa zika*. So it's not the
תנופה tnufa. *tnufa* which came earlier. So רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* so
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, it's not so clear. רבי יוחנן
גופא קמיבעיא ליה *Rabbi Yochanan gufa kamibaia lei*, we want to know
what's פשט *pshat* in רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*. מכדי פשיטא ליה לרבי
יוחנן דשחיטה עושה זיקה oseh zika, *Michdi pshita lei l'rabbi Yochanan deshechita
osa zika*, is it clear to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* that it's
only at the moment of שחיטה shechita *shechita* that they become
combined? and the waving is not enough to combine it as a
unit? או דלמא שחיטה shechita פשיטא ליה, obvious that at least by
שחיטה shechita, they become a unit, ותנופה מסתפקא ליה, utenufo mistapka lei,
but he doesn't know about waving, and it says תיקו, teiku, we
don't know. And the difference is, I understand that it might go
back to the sprinkling, but the גמרא Gemara already has it for
granted that the שחיטה shechita, of the כבשים kvasim, is
מקדיש makdish the לחם. lechem Why? I mean, good question, we'll see
when we get to it, but that's what we've taken for granted.
So the status is that certainly if they had the effect of
being מקדיש הלחם, makdish halechem, that's defining it as a unit. The
question is can you go earlier to the תנופה, tnufa which is
a right, a ritual that's done together, but it doesn't yet change
the status of the bread? And that's a good question, whether that
would be enough.
To me it seems to be obvious to be enough, if you
know תורה Torah is saying...
I understand, but maybe it needs to have some הלכתא halachic impact
before it can be considered one unit. So let's take a look.
So a תיקו, teiku, so we don't know. אמר ליה רב יהודה
בר חנינא לרב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, amar lei Rav Yehuda bar
Chanina le-Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua, הא כתיב קדש יהיו לה' לכהן,
ha ketiv kodesh yihyu l'hashem lakohan, בתר תנופה כתיב. batru tenufo ketiv.
The פסוק pasuk of יהיו, yihyu, which is interesting, which is presumably
what רבא Rava is,
the קדש יהיו לה' לכהן kodesh yihyu l'hashem lakohen which we said
before meant that only one of them was מעכב, meakev, but that
says it after the waving. It says it at the very end
of the פרשה. parsha. So you see even after the waving, only
one of them is מעכב, meakev. not both of them. ופליגי דננס
ורבי עקיבא, upligi de-Nanos ve-Rabbi Akiva, and you still have the
debate based on that פסוק pasuk of קדש, kodesh, which is it
referring to? So you see they're debating even after the waving, even
after the waving. Gemara says one minute, that doesn't prove anything. ולטעמיך
בתר תנופה ולא בתר שחיטה? u-letaamach batar tenufo v-lo batar shechita? What,
do you think that פסוק pasuk קדש יהיו kodesh yihyu only is
written after the waving? That's written at the end of the whole
פרשה, parsha, at the end of the whole section. It speaks about
you waved it, you שחט shachted it, you brought it, and at
the end of the section says קדש יהיו לה' לכהן. kodesh yihyu
l'hashem lakohan.
So, אלא, ela, so what, maybe you'd want to infer that even
after שחיטה Shechita, they're separate units? But we're not saying that. אלא
מאי אית לך למימר? ela mai itlach le-meimar? How do you deal
with this פסוק? pasuk? מעיקרא קאי. meikara ka-ei. It's referring to what
it was at an earlier stage. ומאי קדש יהיו לה' לכהן? u-mai
kodesh yihyu l'hashem lakohen? דבר שסופו לכהן. davar she-sofo l'kohen. What it
meant is this thing originally קדש יהיו לה' לכהן kodesh yihyu l'hashem
lakohen was going to God for the כהן, kohen, but it's not
referring to after the שחיטה Shechita, or after the תנופה. tnufa It
refers to this is the way it was. It was something that
was קדש לה' לכהן. kodesh l'hashem lakohen. Again, the whole problem of
the גמרא Gemara is it reads the פסוק pasuk of קדש יהיו
לה' לכהן kodesh yihyu l'hashem lakohen that the יהיו, yihyu, קדש יהיו
לה' לכהן kodesh yihyu l'hashem lakohen is referring to only one of
the two components. And that that's the crux of the debate, which
one is מעכב. meakev So therefore we, now that we're saying that
both are מעכב meakev. after the waving or after the שחיטה Shechita.
and this פסוק pasuk appears at the very end, we have to
say that this פסוק pasuk refers to what the status was earlier
on. הכא נמי, hacha nami, here too, דבר שסופו לכהן, davar she-sofo
l'kohen, when you eventually something will go to a כהן, kohen, not
yet now. In an earlier stage before the waving, before the שחיטה,
Shechita that's when only one of them was מעכב. meakev Okay, that's
just the פסוק pasuk of קדש יהיו. kodesh yihyu. Back to now
a conceptual question about whether it is, is this really true that
the שחיטה Shechita, defines it as one unit? So says the גמרא,
Gemara ושחיטה עושה זיקה, v-shechita osa zika, is it really true that
the שחיטה Shechita. makes them connected and defines it as one unit?
Because minimally it happens by the שחיטה Shechita, we're saying. ורמינהי, uraminhi,
I'll ask you. Here we have a ברייתא Baraita about תודה.
Toda Okay, תודה Toda is very much sort of לא מעניינא דיומא
lo meinyana de-yoma because תודה Toda, actually comes with ten loaves of
חמץ, chametz, which is why we don't say מזמור לתודה mizmor letoda
this week, because it comes with חמץ. chametz. So let's take a
look at the relationship of the תודה Toda to its bread. It
comes with actually 40 loaves: 30 loaves of מצה, matza, 10 loaves
of חמץ, chametz, that's what the תודה Toda comes with. You give
one of each, there are four different types of bread: three types
of מצה, matza, one type, ten loaves of each. One type of
חמץ. chametz. You give one loaf of each to the כהן. kohen.
The תודה, Toda the bread of the תודה Toda. like the תודה
Toda, itself is eaten in all of ירושלים Yerushalayim and the remainder
gets eaten by the owner. So similarly by the תודה Toda there's
a relationship to the קרבן korban and the bread, and the bread
does not become sanctified only until the קרבן Korban is שחט. Shecht
So let's take a look. That seems to be a good analogy.
Let's take a look at how this plays out by a תודה.
Todah. So let's take a look at this ברייתא. Baraita. עד שלא
שחטה, ad shelo shachta, before you שחט Shecht the bread, the תודה,
Todah נפרס לחמה, nifras lachma, a piece of the bread broke off.
For some reason we're assuming that if a piece of the bread
broke off and one piece is not whole, all of the bread
is invalid. רש"י Rashi is not exactly clear where the גמרא Gemara,
knows that from. He says maybe it's by an association with the
לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. Wherever it's from, there's an assumption that if
you don't have all full loaves, the entire collection of bread is
all invalid. So this invalidity occurred, what we're going to do, this
is a very well-structured ברייתא. Baraita. It's going to talk about three
types of invalidity: bread breaking, the bread becoming טמא, Tamei. and the
bread going יוצא Yotzei to the wrong place, which because it's a
תודה Todah means outside of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, not outside of the מקדש.
And then it starts to say each one of those sequentially, when
did that happen? Does it happen before שחיטה, Shechita after שחיטה, Shechita
or even after זריקה? zerika? Okay, let's take a look. And what
is the consequences? So let's take a look. עד שלא נשחטה נפסל
הלחם, Ad shelo nishchata nifsal halechem, if the piece of bread broke
away before שחיטה, Shechita no problem.
Meaning any of the forty breads you mean?
Any of the forty breads. So no problem. Anything that happens before
שחיטה, Shechita you can correct, you can fix. So what do you
do?
יביא לחם אחר ושופרה. Yavi lechem acher v'shofre. Not all forty, just
one of them, right? Right, you fix that one. Correct. Okay. מששחטה
נפסל לחמה, Misheshachata nifsal lachmah, if the piece of bread broke after
שחיטה. Shechitah So now you can't fix it because the שחיטה Shechitah,
defined the relationship with the bread, it sanctified the bread, etc. can't
be fixed at this stage, it can't be substituted. So הדם יזרק
והבשר יאכל וידי נדרו לא יצא. Hadam yizarek vehabasar yeachel viydei nidro
lo yatza. So go ahead sprinkle the blood and eat the meat,
but you will not fulfill your obligation of a תודה. Todah. Why?
Because essentially now this is a קרבן Korban that had to be
brought without the bread. The whole bread is invalid, okay? Because the
פסול Pasul, happened after
שחיטה, Shechitah, after
defined, right, now you can't bring thirty-nine that are okay, one broken
piece פוסל's Posel the whole bread, for whatever reason. So now you
have פסול Pasul bread, you can't substitute it, the קרבן's Korban, already
been שחטed, Shecht okay? So what do you do? So you bring
the קרבן, Korban but it's brought without bread. What's a תודה Todah.
without bread? A שלמים. Shelamim. Okay, so therefore it essentially becomes a
שלמים. Shelamim. רש"י Rashi says you have כוונה Kavanah when you're זורק
הדם Zorek hadam to make it like a שלמים, Shelamim, yes. It
could also be that you don't need כוונה, Kavanah, could be that
it automatically becomes a שלמים, Shelamim, like the whole discussion about a
פסח Pesach בשאר ימות השנה. Bish'ar yemot hashanah. But either way, a
תודה Todah, is a type of a שלמים, Shelamim, so without its
bread, it reverts to being a standard שלמים. Shelamim. But that's why
you don't fulfill your obligation, because then it turns out you brought
a שלמים, Shelamim, you didn't bring a תודה. Todah, Okay, that's what
happens if it happens after שחיטה.
Shechitah And you burn the bread?
And you burn the bread, correct. Okay, they burned the bread?
They baked the bread before they שחטed.
Shecht They had all the bread baked before they שחטed, Shecht yes.
Okay. והלחם פסול, Vehalechem pasul, the לחם Lechem is invalid and you
have to burn it. נזרק הדם. Nizrak hadam. Now, let's say the
bread got a piece broke off after the blood was sprinkled. So
after the blood was sprinkled, the קרבן Korban was already defined. As
soon as you sprinkle the blood and you have all the bread
around, you now were יצא Yotzei your תודה. Todah. So anything goes
wrong now, it just affects what you can eat, but not whether
the קרבן Korban. was valid, because you already sprinkled the blood. So
נזרק הדם, Nizrak hadam, תורמין מן השלם על הפרוס. Tormin min hashaleim
al haparus. So you give the כהן Kohen his four, four loaves,
you don't give him a broken loaf, you have to give because
a broken is פסול, Pasul. like we said before. You have to
give him a whole loaf, okay? So you give him four, four
whole loaves and they count, like you know, they're working for the
remainder loaves, even though one of the remainder loaves is broken.
And then you can eat the other thirty-five?
And you can eat the others, right.
No, the other thirty-five? The broken one just gets burnt?
Yes.
I mean you could have even thought that maybe it doesn't become
פסול Pasul if it happens after the שחיטה, Shechitah, after the זריקה.
Zrika. Because after the זריקה Zrika you're going to be eating the
bread anyway, right? So it's even a question of... so let's finish
this. Okay, so anyway... מן השלם על הפרוס. Min hashaleim al haparus.
Okay, and that's it. Now, so correctly Michael says,
and רש"י Rashi actually when he says why you have to give
the כהן Kohen the שלם Shaleim quotes a separate פסוק Pasuk that
learns that like a כהן Kohen should get a שלם Shaleim not
a פרוס. Parus. And presumably here actually once the blood is sprinkled,
it could very well be that the breaking doesn't invalidate, if the
breaking invalidated the bread you wouldn't give anything to the כהן. Kohen.
And look, what are you going to do with the bread now
after the blood is sprinkled? You're going to eat it. You don't
say as soon as you start eating it, oh my God, it's
a פרוס Parus and now it's פסול. Pasul, So it could very
well be that after the, if it breaks after the sprinkling, it
all remains כשר, Kasher, there's just a technical point that you should
not give the כהן Kohen a broken piece, you should give the
כהן Kohen a full loaf. Okay, so that's what happens about the
breaking of the bread. Okay, so now we're going to go to
the same three steps by the two other פסולים. Psulim. Let's take
a look.
Okay, where are we?
Okay. עד שלא נשחטה יצא הלחם, Ad shelo nishchata yatza halechem, if
before שחיטה Shechitah the bread went outside of the, not the מקדש,
but outside of ירושלים, Yerushalayim. because it's the תודה, Todah, what matters,
the גבול Gvul is ירושלים Yerushalayim. and the same by the bread.
So if it happened before you שחטed Shecht it, no big deal.
It's only קדושת דמים Kedushat damim now, it's not קדושת הגוף. Kedushat
haguf. You can bring something that's owned by the בית המקדש out
of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it doesn't invalidate. So מחזירו, Machziro, bring it back
in, you don't even need new bread, just bring this bread back
in, the bread didn't become invalid, okay? Because it's not yet קדושת
הגוף. Kedushat haguf. ושוחט V'shochet and then you can שחט Shecht the
קרבן. Korban, מששחטה יצא הלחם, Misheshachata yatza halechem, if after you שחטed
shachted it the bread went outside of ירושלים. Yerushalayim, So from the
moment of שחיטה Shechitah the bread gets קדושת הגוף, Kedushat haguf, cannot
be brought out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim, You brought it out of ירושלים,
you've invalidated the bread. And the קרבן, Korban the blood has not
yet been sprinkled. So you've invalidated the bread before sprinkling the blood.
So what are you going to do? So הדם יזרק והבשר יאכל
וידי נדרו לא יצא. Hadam yizarek vehabasar yeachel viydei nidro lo yatza.
So now you have a קרבן Korban, without valid bread, so you
can go ahead bring the קרבן, Korban, sprinkle the blood, eat the
meat, but it's a שלמים, Shelamim, it's not a תודה, Todah and
therefore you do not fulfill your obligation. Okay, so you get it
here, after שחיטה Shechitah, again, the central theme here is that after
שחיטה shechita? it becomes קדושת הגוף Kedushat haguf and things can't, once
something becomes פסול Pasul, you don't have an option to replace it,
the animal's already שחטed, so you have to do with the consequence.
What does it mean to not have the bread? So if it
broke after שחיטה shchitah or it was יוצא Yotzei after שחיטה, shchitah
the bread became invalid, but so you can go ahead and bring
the קרבן, Korban but it’s without bread which makes it no longer
a תודה. Todah והלחם פסול VeHaLechem Pasul the bread is invalid. נזרק
הדם, Nizrak HaDam, now after the bread is sprinkled, the bread, the
blood is sprinkled, the קרבן Korban was totally כשר, Kasher the bread
was brought out, so fine, that bread that's brought out is יוצא
Yotzei and can't be eaten, but everything else is fine. תורם ממה
שבפנים על שבחוץ, Torem Mimah SheBifnim Al SheBichutz, you don't give the
כהן Kohen the bread that's פסול, Pasul you don't give the כהן
Kohen the bread that was taken outside, you give the כהן Kohen
the כשר bread that was still remained in ירושלים, and therefore, but
you go ahead and you can eat all the remainder bread, you
can eat, the כהן Kohen eats his bread, you eat your bread
that stayed in ירושלים, you don't eat the loaves that went out,
they became פסול, Pasul, but the קרבן Korban was a good תודה,
Todah. okay? So again, it’s the same rule. It's exactly the same
rule, right, I mean we're just going through all the cases, but
it's totally the same, the only difference we're going to see now
is the third case of טומאה. Tumah. Okay, but it's exactly the
same, exactly.
Now,
what if נטמא לחמה, Nitma Lachmah, what if it became טמא? Tamei,
Did I skip a line?
No okay, עד שלא שחטה נטמא לחמה, Ad SheLo Shachtah Nitma Lachmah,
let’s say it became the bread became טמא. Tamei So if that
happened before שחיטה, shechita, so what do you do? So fine, before
שחיטה shechita anything can be fixed.
מביא לחם אחר ושוחט Mevi Lechem Acher VeShochet and he slaughters. מששחטה,
MisheShachtah, now it was slaughtered, so the bread has קדושת הגוף, Kedushat
HaGuf, it becomes טמא, Tamei? so you can't bring substitute bread, and
so now you have פסול Pasul, bread. So נטמא לחמה, Nitma Lachmah,
so here הדם יזרק והבשר יאכל ובידי נדרו יצא, HaDam Yizareik VeHaBasar
Ye’achel UVidei Nidro Yatza, you actually fulfill your obligation. Why? You had
טמא Tamei, bread. שהציץ מרצה על הטמא, SheHaTzitz Mertzeh Al HaTamei, the
ציץ Tzitz fixes טומאה Tumah problems. Now, it's quite interesting actually, because
normally the ציץ Tzitz fixes טומאה Tumah problems בדיעבד, Bidi’avad, you're not
supposed to be זורק דם, Zorek Dam, but here, what's טמא? Tamei,
It's not that the קרבן Korban, is טמא, Tamei it's the bread
is טמא, Tamei. so you have a total license to be זורק
הדם, Zorek HaDam, you don't need the ציץ Tzitz to allow you
to be זורק הדם. Zorek HaDam. The only problem you have is
does this count as a תודה Todah or as a שלמים? Shelamim?
Was the דם Dam being נזרק Nizrak on an animal with bread
or not? So you're זורק דם Zorek Dam even לכתחילה Lichatchilah because
of the ציץ, Tzitz, we're allowed to gloss over the fact that
the bread is נטמא, Nitma, where you don't eat the bread, but
in terms of the question of the validity of the קרבן, Korban
we look at it as if the bread was not נטמא Nitma
and it counts as a תודה Todah and you're יוצא Yotzei, your
obligation.
Okay, so there's an exception to what we said before.
והלחם פסול, VeHaLechem Pasul, the bread remains פסול, psul the ציץ Tzitz
doesn't let you eat טמא Tamei. things, but it considered it as
if the bread was fully present
and therefore then if you did eat it, then accidentally then you
wouldn't be over because the ציץ Tzitz does מכפר Mechaper on טומאה
בשוגג, Tumah BiShogeg, right?
No, טומאה בשוגג Tumah BiShogeg is the whole case since about you
know about the special קרבן Korban. of עולה ויורד. Oleh VeYored. The
ציץ Tzitz works for not your personal עבירה Aveirah but for the
ריצוי Ritzuy of the קרבן. Korban Okay,
so, okay, so that's what we have there, that the bread remains
פסול, pasul but vis-à-vis the validity of the קרבן Korban it counted
as a תודה. Todah נזרק הדם, Nizrak HaDam, now let's say the
blood was sprinkled and then it became טמא. Tamei So okay, the
קרבן Korban you were fully יוצא and now you have to just
deal with for consequence that one loaf from bread is טמא. Tamei,
So what do you do? תורם מן הטהור על הטמא, Torem Min
HaTahor Al HaTamei, obviously you're not going to eat the טמא Tamei
and you're not going to give the כהן Kohen the טמא, tamei
so you give the כהן Kohen the טהור Tahor bread, you’re going
to eat the טהור Tahor that remained, and you know the קרבן
Korban is totally good and it’s a good תודה Todah and the
one טמא tamei bread loaf you get rid of. Okay, so a
very nicely structured ברייתא, Braisa, right? Very well organized, very goes through
it sequentially, okay fine. What do we see from all of this?
We see that after you שחט it, if a problem arose after
שחיטה, shechita טומאה, Tumah, יוצא, whatever, the consequence is what do you
do is that the bread becomes invalid and it becomes a שלמים,
Shelamim, it becomes a קרבן korban, without bread. But we've got a
problem. If שחיטה shechting עושה זיקה, zika the שחיטה shechting makes it
one unit, so now it’s one cohesive unit, if any part of
it is invalid, you should have to throw everything out. Why are
you allowed to salvage this as a שלמים? Shelamim? That's the question.
There is one extra question see yeah,
so you're תורם מן השלם על הפרוס Torem Min HaShalem Al HaParus
may also be different in the first case versus the other three.
Because the first case you may say you may be able to
eat all of them just that you don't want to give the
כהן Kohen a broken piece, whereas in the other one like that
one piece of bread may be,
yeah presumably, I'd have to check that, but presumably the פרוס parus
is not even a פסול pasul there after זריקה. Zrikah. Okay, so
let's take a look. ואי סלקא דעתך דשחיטה עושה זיקה, Ve’i Salka
Da’atach DeShechitah Oseh Zikah, if שחיטה really makes it connected, the animal
with the bread, כיון דהוקדשו זה וזה בשחיטה, Keivan DeHukdeshu Zeh VeZeh
BeShechitah, once they are connected to one another through the act of
שחיטה, they become one coherent unit, if so, ואי הכי לחם נמי
ליפסל ותודה נמי תיפסל? Ei hachi lechem nami lipasel veTodah nami tipasel?
When the bread becomes invalid, the תודה Todah should become invalid. Why
should you be able to salvage this as a שלמים Shelamim and
dump the bread but
have this have independent status? So the גמרא Gemara says no. שאני
תודה דרחמנא קרייה שלמים. Shani Todah DeRachmana Karyei Shelamim. The תורה Torah
calls the תודה Toda שלמים. Shelamim. It says: על זבח תודת שלמיו,
Al Zevach Todat Shelamav, it calls the תודה Toda שלמים. Shelamim. מה
שלמים קריבים בלא לחם אף תודה קריבה בלא לחם. Mah Shelamim Kereivim
Belo Lechem Af Todah Kereivah Belo Lechem. The same way שלמים Shelamim
is without bread, the תודה Toda, is valid without bread. תודה Toda
can exist without the bread, which might mean that it automatically reverts
to a שלמים. Shelamim. רש"י Rashi says you need כוונה, kavana, but
anyway it automatically is somewhat can revert to a שלמים Shelamim when
it doesn't have the תודה Toda status, which means that by a
תודה, Toda yes, it's one unit, but it also always retains also
the potential of being independent from the bread, which does not exist
as the גמרא Gemara by the שתי הלחם. Shtei ha-Lechem Now of
course the problem is that the שתי הלחם Shtei ha-Lechem is also
called שלמים. Shelamim. It calls the lambs שלמים. Shelamim. But רש"י, Rashi,
but you know רש"י Rashi or תוספות Tosafot say, well, but we
never have that idea though that there exists, first of all, there
never exists, there's no שלמי ציבור Shalmei Tzibur other than the שתי
הלחם. Shtei ha-Lechem, You don't even have a category really of שלמים
Shelamim that exists in the תורה Torah of שלמי ציבור without the
bread. So it could be that once they are defined as a
unit, you do know, there does not see this as the ability
to go to revert to some status of שלמים Shelamim without the
bread. But here, that is always a possible status to revert to.
So the point is it was a good comparison, but maybe תודה
Toda, functions differently. תודה Toda, can exist, the bread can be separated
off and it can continue to exist. But since this, the way
I would reframe it is, since this is all about the שתי
הלחם, Shtei ha-Lechem the תודה toda is fundamentally about the קרבן, korban.
the לחם lechem, is an additional piece of it that makes it
a תודה, toda but even when they get unified you can break
off the bread and still have it as a קרבן. korban Here
fundamentally it's about bringing the שתי הלחם Shtei ha-Lechem, and therefore once
they get to a unit, meaning we can debate can you in
theory have one without the other, and בן ננס Ben Nanas can
even say you can have the lambs without the bread. But I
would like to think that even בן ננס Ben Nanas would not
disagree, although the גמרא Gemara sounds absolutely different, we'll see in a
minute. But I would like to think that even בן ננס Ben
Nanas does not disagree that the fundamental קרבן korban here is the
שתי הלחם Shtei ha-Lechem, and therefore once it is defined as a
unit then you need them to come together. You cannot break off,
you don't have one without the
other, as the משנה mishnah תני tni now.
Well, what at least a שיטה shita as made even here.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on. אמר רב ירמיה, Amar
Rav Yirmeya, אם תימצי לומר im timtza lomar תנופה tnufa עושה זיקה,
zikah let's play with the possibility that the waving makes them one
unit. So אבד הלחם avad ha-lechem so first we're going to start
with some obvious context to get to our question. So you did
the תנופה tnufa, and now the bread got lost. אבדו כבשים, avdu
kvasim, the lambs are lost, meaning are as good as lost. You
wait, you know, you basically the lambs are פסול pasul once the
bread is lost and you have to let them die. So אבדו
כבשים, avdu kvasim, if the lambs are lost, אבד הלחם, avad ha-lechem,
you have to burn the bread. Okay, obviously they're one unit, they're
one unit, one is lost and you can't use the other part.
ואם תימצי לומר ve-im timtza lomar תנופה tnufa אינו עושה זיקה, eino
osah zika, now what if the תנופה tenufa does not make זיקה
zika, like we've been working with until now, that they only become
a unit until שחיטה? So הביא לחם וכבשים והונפו, heivi lechem ve-kvasim
ve-hunfu, so now you brought the lambs and the bread and you
did תנופה. tenufa? ואבד הלחם ve-avad ha-lechem and then the bread got
טמא or lost, you
brought new bread. So now we have an interesting case. You brought
substitute bread but the lambs have already been waved. Anybody who's ever
learned יומא, Yoma, you know, knows that this is like a standard
thing. What happens, because there's all the discussion about the שעיר לעזאזל
se'ir la-azazel and the שעיר בפנים se'ir bifnim and what happens right
now, like you, you know, you're three steps into the עבודה avoda
of the of the שעיר בפנים se'ir bifnim and the שעיר לעזאזל
se'ir la-azazel gets lost, can you match it up at a middle
stage? So anyway here you're matching it up at a middle stage.
You've waved the lambs already, the bread got טמא or lost, you
brought new bread. How do you deal with it that you have
waved lambs and unwaved bread? Do you do the תנופה tenufa, again
or not? Can you just go forward or do you have to
do the תנופה tenufa again? Okay, so what do you do? אותו
הלחם טעון תנופה או אינו טעון תנופה? oso ha-lechem taun tnufa o
eino taun tnufa? Do you have to wave this this new bread?
Or now what about if it's the reverse? Let's the lambs got
lost or or פסול and you had to bring new lambs. So
then you would have the reverse, you'd have waved bread and unwaved
lambs. Would you have to wave the lambs again? So גמרא Gemara
says that's obviously not a pro. אבדו כבשים לא תיבעי לך. avdu
kvasim lo tiba'ei lach. I have no question if the lambs got
lost after the waving what the הלכה halacha would be. דודאי בעו
תנופה de-vadai ba'u tnufa that you definitely would have to wave the
lambs again. Why? So רש"י Rashi says because the
פסוק pasuk because the פסוק pasuk says והניף הכהן
אתם על לחם הבכרים תנופה לפני ה' על שני כבשים. ve-henif ha-kohen
otam al lechem ha-bikkurim tnufa lifnei Hashem al shenei kvasim. So he's
going to wave them, the two lambs he just mentioned, on the
bread. So the emphasis is on the waving of the lambs. So
other way to understand this is, now again, if you ask normal
per, you know, again, I think for me, I don't know, abnormal
person thinks about שתי הלחם, Shtei ha-Lechem but okay, if you ask
me about it the same, I think that the עיקר ikar קרבן
korban is the שתי הלחם Shetei ha-Lechem because that's the way, not
because the פסוקים psukim really, but I think that's again the, I
mean, maybe the פסוקים, psukim, you know, it's the עומר Omer and
the counterpart of the עומר Omer is the שתי הלחם, Shetei ha-Lechem
and we're focusing on the grain and that seems to be it's
not just like the bread to the תודה, toda it seems to
be the focus. Certainly in the גמרא, Gemara this is a קרבן
korban of the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem. it's not the קרבן korban
of the כבשים, kvasim the כבשים kevasim. are always just what comes
with it. So I would have thought that maybe if the שתי
הלחם shtei halechem are the עיקר ikar the תנופה tenufa is the
עיקר. ikar. And the תנופה, tenufa I mean the תנופה tenufa on
the שתי... Shtei... the לחם is the עיקר ikar that that it
have to be on the bread. But both the פסוק pasuk emphasizes
the lambs and also it seems that part of the assumption here
is most of the things that are waved are things on which
an act of הקרבה hakrava is done. You know, I mean it's
not really true about the, I mean normally if you like wave
the חזה chazeh and the שוק shok and you wave things, you're
waving from a part of the קרבן korban that's הוקרב. hukrav.
You know and the שתי הלחם shtei halechem even if they're connected
to the קרבן korban is not exactly הוקרב. hukrav. Now by the
ביכורים, Bikkurim, right, right by the, yeah by there's not a real,
you're just מניח maniach the ביכורים, Bikkurim, right?
So
what does it say by the ביכורים? Bikkurim? It
says ולקח הכהן הטנא מידך V’lakach ha-kohen ha-tene mi-yadecha והניחו ve-hiniho לפני
מזבח ה' אלהיך lifnei mizbe'ach Hashem Elokecha
וענית ואמרת לפני ה'
אלהיך. ve-anita ve-amarta
lifnei Hashem Elokecha.
Yeah,
do you do תנופה tenufa, with the
ביכורים? Bikkurim? What's not in the פסוקים pesukim but I think they
might learn it out from the ולקח ve-lakach and והניחו ve-hiniho and
so on.
I gotta tell
you, good thing we're doing דף היומי Daf Yomi because I
forgot half of this stuff.
What?
You wave but then it's higher. Lamb is very heavy.
You do two of them.
I didn't know our lambs were so heavy, they're not cows. Well,
yeah, but well,
I don't know.
If I were him I wouldn't want to eat
the bread after got licked
all over by a,
you know. Right, hold on. What?
A live lamb was on my bread, I wouldn't want to eat
the bread.
Oh come on, what are you talking about? It's a nice sandwich.
What?
Once it's cooked? Once it's cooked, fine.
Do you like
sliced beef
on your, a sandwich of sliced beef?
Wait
one minute. Slide, it's dog, catchy.
If a dog licked my bread, that's not good, I don't like
that. I'm saying buddy, but a lamb moves around, you know, and
like drool on it or something, I don't know, or lick the
bread. I think they can do whatever they want on the bread.
כל המביא
ביכורים טעון שיר וקרבן ושיר ותנופה
ולינה.
Kol ha-meivi
Bikkurim
ta'un shir ve-korban ve-shir
u-tenufa ve-lina.
So what's this תנופה? tenufa. תנופה, tenufa. one minute, yeah. ומוריד הסל
מעל כתפו ואוחז בשפתיו והכהן
מניח ידו תחתיו ומניף וקורא ארמי
אובד אבי.
u-morid ha-sal me-al ktefo ve-ochez bisfatav ve-ha-kohen maniach yado tachtav
u-manif ve-kore Arami oved
avi.
So
ביכורים Bikkurim would be an example where you do תנופה tenufa on
something that you don't actually do a הקרבה hakrava on. You present
it to the כהן kohen but you don't actually do a הקרבה
hakrava, on. So it could in theory have a תנופה tenufa that
emphasizes the שתי הלחם shtei halechem and not emphasizing the כבשים. kevasim.
But either because of the פסוק pasuk or just because more classically,
you know, the תנופה tenufa is done on the thing that you
do the הקרבה, hakravah the גמרא Gemara here is taking it for
granted that this תנופה tenufa has to be done on the כבשים.
kevasim, So therefore what he's saying is the following: if you had
to replace one of the components after תנופה, tenufa so if the
component that had to be replaced were the כבשים, kevasim it obviously
has to do another תנופה. tenufa. You can't have כבשים kevasim without
תנופה. tenufa? That's his assumption. Okay, כי תיבעי לך ki tiba'i lach
but that's obvious.
Okay, and we're saying at some point are we saying that it
is a unit?
Yes, no, it's not a unit that we're working in the הוה
אמינא hava amina that תנופה tenufa is not עושה זיקה. zika. So
we're allowed to replace a unit and now that allows us to
explore this interesting question of whether you have to do what if
one of the things had תנופה tenufa. and not the other? Now
you can never do תנופה tenufa sing, singly by itself, תנופה tenufa
has to be together. So we're only able to explore this question
if we think תנופה tenufa is not עושה זיקה. zika So therefore
since it's not עושה זיקה, you're allowed to replace one of the
components after תנופה. tenufa. And now we get to ask does it
require another תנופה? tnufah Which component must have תנופה tnufah. done to
it?
But if you think it has to be on the לחם, so
the, meaning if you're going to,
if you're going to do it again you'll do it again with
the lambs.
Okay, so the question.
But you don't have, do you have to? Maybe only the כבשים
kevasim really require תנופה. tnufah And the כבשים kevasim. had a תנופה
tnufah. with bread. Now you have new bread but the תנופה tnufah.
was really only required for the sake of the כבשים. kevasim. So
that's the גמרא's Gemara question. It's taking it for granted that it
is required for the sake of the כבשים. kevasim The question is:
is it only required for the sake of the כבשים kvassim or
is it even required for the sake of the bread? Okay, so
let's read that again. So אבדו כבשים, avdu kevasim, five lines down,
אבדו כבשים לא תיבעי לך. avdu kevasim lo tiba’i lach. If the
lambs are lost, that's not my question. דודאי בעו תנופה. devadai ba'u
tenufa. Certainly תנופה tnufah is required with the bread and you would
do it with the, what you do with the new lambs and
the old bread. Right? That certainly requires תנופה. tnufah כי תיבעי לך
אבדו. ki tiba’i lach avdu. My question is that the bread is
lost. Now maybe this played out between רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, and
בן ננס. Ben Nanas. Let's take a look. דאליבא דבן ננס, Daliba
d'Ben Nanas, now remember, בן ננס Ben Nanas says the כבשים kvassim
are עיקר, ikar, okay? So דאליבא דבן ננס daliba d'Ben Nanas לא
תיבעי לך, lo tiba'i lach, דאמר כבשים עיקר. d'amar kvassim ikar. He
emphasizes that the כבשים kvassim, can come by themselves, so that means
that they exist independently, so therefore the bread יהיו yihyu is something
that comes through the כבשים, kvassim. so the focus is on the
כבשים. kvassim So therefore you wouldn't need it on the bread alone.
Now again to me, I don't see why that's obvious, just because
you know you can't have bread without the כבשים kvassim, doesn't mean
that when they come together the focus doesn't shift to the bread.
But here the גמרא Gemara really is saying that according to בן
ננס, Ben Nanas, you know, the focus is on the lambs, not
on the bread, which is not how we normally think of שתי
הלחם. shtei halechem So according to him, the תנופה tnufah, would not
be required for the bread. כי תיבעי לך אליבא דרבי עקיבא. Ki
tiba'i lach aliba d'Rabbi Akiva. The question is according to רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva, that said that the bread can come alone, which gives
independent status to the bread. So maybe the bread would require תנופה.
tnufah
דאמר לחם עיקר, d'amar lechem ikar, so the bread is the fundamental.
מאי, Mai, what do you say?
דאמר לחם עיקר, d'amar lechem ikar, מאי, mai, where are we?
מאי. Mai. כיון דלחם עיקר בעי תנופה, Keivan d'lechem ikar ba'ei tnufah,
since it is the focus, the fundamental piece, you should need to
wave the bread even if you've waved the lambs? או דילמא, O
dilma, or we say, כיון דמתירין דידיה כבשים נינהו לא צריך תנופה,
keivan d'matirin didey kvassim ninhu lo tzarich tnufah, since the thing that's
מתיר matir the bread, which is the כבשים, kvassim does not require
תנופה—it tnufa requires it, but it means it's already been done—so it
does not require a new תנופה. So therefore,
I'm sorry, I put the comma in the wrong place. כיון דמתירין
דידיה כבשים, keivan d'matirin didey kvassim, since it's the כבשים kevasim, that
are מתיר matir the bread, so the bread still is dependent on
the lambs even according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, so therefore
לא צריך תנופה, lo tzarich tnufah, therefore it would not require תנופה.
So the גמרא Gemara says תיקו, teiku, we don't know. So again
here the גמרא is again assuming, notice, that according to רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, even if the bread is עיקר, ikar, when they come
together, the same way the גמרא said before when they come together
it creates זיקה through the שחיטה that there is a link, so
here it's also assuming that when they come together, the שחיטה of
the lambs—the lambs is the מתיר matir of the bread. So according
to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, this is exactly why בן ננס Ben
Nanas argues on רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, but the גמרא is saying
according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva when the bread comes by itself,
it works without a מתיר, matir, you know, you just present the
bread or wave it or who knows what, but when it comes
with the lambs, then the lambs are the things that are the
מתיר, matir, are the act of הקרבה hakravah for the bread. And
therefore, to ask the following conceptual question according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, it's coming with the lambs. So now רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva?
admits that the lambs are the way in which you bring the
bread. Does that somewhat shift the center of gravity? Conceptually the bread
is עיקר, ikar, but with the lambs, the lambs are being מתיר
matir the bread. And the question is, if you had the תנופה
from the lambs without the bread because of this case, it got
lost and substituted, so in that type of a situation, would you
need to do תנופה on the bread? Or do you say since
when it's coming with the lambs, the lambs are the מתיר, matir,
and therefore, and the lambs have the תנופה, you don't need the
תנופה on the bread itself? So it says תיקו. teiku. So again
what is interesting is the גמרא is conceptualizing one, according to בן
ננס, Ben Nanas, it's saying that even though בן ננס, Ben Nanas,
that it's making this association that if it, based on whether it
can come independently, determines what is עיקר. ikar. So according to בן
ננס, Ben Nanas, what we normally call the קרבן korban of שתי
הלחם shtei halechem, should maybe be called the קרבן korban of the
שני כבשים, shnei kvassim, okay? That the lambs are עיקר. ikar. And
according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva? it's particularly interesting because he said
the bread is עיקר, ikar, which makes sense, and can come by
itself. But then when it comes with the lambs, then it does
function then more as a unit and through the הקרבה of the
lambs. Okay, so now we are going to continue with this along
the line,
the very המוציא Hamotzi maker, you're still פטור patur for the...
there you go. Okay, so אמר ליה אביי לרבא. Amar lei Abaye
l'Rava. So now אביי Abaye said to רבא Rava the following question.
Now here he's going back to an earlier stage in the משנה,
because remember we had in the משנה that the עולה olah that
comes with the שתי
הלחם—the shtei halechem one cow, two rams, and seven
sheep—is not מעכב meakev the שתי הלחם shtei halechem and the שתי
הלחם is not מעכב meakev, it. That there's no real relationship. So
he's going to say, well, why? You know, why is it that
all these things come with the שתי הלחם, why do we give
greater weight to the two lambs and make them one unit when
you שוחט shochet it and at least in one direction it's מעכב,
maakve, and why do we make that the whole big עולה olah
that comes with it, the one, seven, and two, the one, two,
and seven, you know, that has no relationship with the bread? Is
that question clear? By which is particularly if you were here yesterday,
you understand that that's not the קרבן מוסף. korban musaf. The קרבן
מוסף korban musaf is written over in פנחס. Pinchas. Here's the קרבן
korban that the תורה Torah says is brought with the bread, but
הלכתית halachtit is not dependent on the bread and the bread isn't
dependent on it. And they exist completely independently. So that's going to
be אביי's Abaye question. Let's take a look. So אמר ליה אביי
לרבא, Amar lei Abaye l'Rava, so אביי Abaye said to רבא, Rava,
מאי שנא שני כבשים דמקדשי לחם ומעכבי? Mai shna shnei kvassim d'makdeshi
lechem u'meakvi? How is the שני כבשים shnei kvassim different that they
are—that the slaughtering of the lambs sanctifies the bread, presumably even according
to רבי עקיבא? That's what we've been saying. And they exist completely
independently. So that's going to be אביי's Abaye question. Let's take a
look. So אמר ליה אביי לרבא, Amar lei Abaye l'Rava, אביי Abaye
said to רבא, Rava, מאי שנא שני כבשים דמקדשי לחם ומעכבי, Mai
shna shnei kevasim d'makdshei lacham u'maakvei, how is the שני כבשים shnei
kevasim different that they are, that they the slaughtering of the lamb
sanctifies the bread, presumably even according to רבי עקיבא? That's what we've
been saying, and therefore it's מעכבי, maakvei, and it is they are
מעכבי maakvei one another, at least in one direction, or you could
say even better, once there's שחיטה, there's זיקה, and then they're both
things are מעכבי maakvei once the שחיטה occurred. That's what we're saying
by the שתי הלחם ומאי שנא שבעה כבשים ופר ואילים u'mai shna
shiva kevasim u'par v'eilim and how's that different from the seven כבשים,
kevasim the פר par and the אילים—by eilim the way that's the
exact order they're written in the תורה, Torah, seven כבשים then the
פר par then the אילים—דלא מקדשי לחם, we don't say their slaughtering
sanctifies the bread, we never said their שחיטה is מקדש בלחם mikadesh
balachem ולא מעכבי, v'lo maakvei, and after they've been slaughtered, there's no
זיקה. We never said the slaughtering of them connects them to the
bread and now if you're missing one, you miss the other. So
why do these completely remain independent? So אמר ליה, amar lei, he
said there's a difference. הוב והוזקו זה לזה בתנופה. Hov vehuzku ze
laze bitnufa. The תורה Torah is very clear that you only wave
the bread and the lambs together, so therefore that is really one
unit. And we says the lamb sanctify and there's זיקה and then
it's מעכב, maakve these things are coming as a part of the
package but they never get defined as a unit together with the
bread. גמרא says one minute, תנופה does not always make define things.
והרי תודה דלא הוזקו זה לזה בתנופה, V'harei toda de-lo huzku ze
la-ze bi-tnufa, you don't wave the תודה toda, with its bread ומקדשא
ומעכבא, u-makdsha u-maakva, and by the תודה toda the slaughtering of the
תודה toda. sanctifies the bread and is מעכב maakve at least in
one direction. If you don't have the תודה, toda. you don't bring
the bread. And you could say it's actually מעכב maakve in two
directions in the sense that if you don't have the bread it
no longer counts as a תודה toda anyway. It might be count
as a שלמים shelamim but it no longer count as a תודה.
toda. So there's no waving there but that's defined as one unit.
So let's say the same thing here with the big עולה ola
and the bread.
אלא כתודה. Ela ke-toda. No, here's the way it's like a תודה.
מה תודה שלמים אף הכא נמי שלמים. Ma toda shelamim af hacha
nami shelamim. By תודה we see that the link of bread to
a קרבן korban exists with a שלמים. shelamim. That's actually a very
nice point. The only time the תורה Torah speaks about bringing bread
whether it's מצה matzah or חמץ chametz with a קרבן korban, is
with a שלמים. shelamim. So if you also bring the שתי הלחם
with a קרבן, korban the קרבן korban. that it's going to be
associated with is the שלמים, shelamim, is the כבשי עצרת kivsei atzeret
and not the עולה. ola. So the גמרא says מי
דמי, mi-dami, it's not similar,
התם ליכא זבחים אחריני בהדיה הכא דאיכא זבחים אחריני בהדיה לקדשו הני
והני.
hatam leika zvachim achrini
bahadei
hacha di-ika zvachim achrini bahadei likdusho hani v-hani. There there were no
other קרבנות, korbanot, so there's no other קרבנות korbanot so the שלמים
shelamim is connected to the תודה. But here where you have שלמים
shelamim and all these עולות, olot, maybe they should all be linked
to the bread and it should not be exclusive to the שלמים
shelamim and the שחיטה of the עולות olot should sanctify the bread
and should create some type of a link. So אלא כאיל נזיר,
ela ke-ayil nazir, let's learn it out from the איל ram of
a נזיר. nazir. So מה איל נזיר אף על גב דאיכא זבחים
אחריני שלמים הוא דמקדש מדי אחריני לא. ma ayil nazir af al
gav de-ika zvachim achrini shelamim hu d'mikadish mid-achrini lo. The איל ram
of a נזיר nazir when a נזיר nazir ends his status is
brought with loaves of bread and there the איל ram is a
שלמים shelamim and there are other קרבנות korbanot that are brought and
the תורה Torah makes it very clear that you take this lamb
and the איל ram and the איל ram is what is associated
with the bread and not the other
קרבנות.
korbanot.
וביום מלאת ימי נזרו, u-v'yom mlot yemey neziru, it says
כבש בן שנתו תמים אחד לעולה, keves ben shanato tamim echad l'ola,
so there's your עולה, ola, וכבשה בת שנתה תמימה לחטאת, v-kivsa bat
shnata tmima l'chatat, ואיל אחד תמים לשלמים, v-ayil echad tamim l'shelamim, so
the איל ayil is שלמים, shelamim, וסל מצות חלת בלולת בשמן ורקיקי
מצות משחים בשמן ומנחתם ונסכיהם, v-sal matzot challot blulot bashamen u'rkikei matzot
mshuchim bashamen u-minchatam v-niskeihem, so there's your bread, והקריב הכהן, v-hikriv hakohein,
so then it says ואת האיל יעשה זבח שלמים לה' על סל
המצות ועשה הכהן את מנחתו ואת נסכו. v'et ha-ayil ya'aseh zevach shelamim
l'Hashem al sal hamatzot v'asah hakohen et minchato v'et nisko. So very
clearly they associate the שלמים, shelamim, the איל ram with the bread
even though there are other קרבנות. korbanot. So you see still bread
is linked with a שלמים shelamim even when there are other קרבנות.
korbanot. So הכא נמי לא שנא, hacha nami lo shna, here too
it's no different. והתם מנלן, ve-hatam minalan, and how do you know
it there? דתניא, d-tanya, ואת האיל יעשה זבח שלמים לה' על סל
המצות, v'et ha-ayil ya'aseh zevach shelamim l'Hashem al sal hamatzot, so you
make that שלמים shelamim with the
מצות, matzot, מלמד שהסל בא חובה לאיל, melamed she-hasal bavo el ha-ayil,
the bread comes because of the איל, ram, it's associated with the
איל ram and the שחיטה of the איל ram of the שלמים
shelamim sanctifies them. לפיכך, lefikach, therefore, שחטו שלא לשמו, shachto shelo lishmo,
if you שחטו shechted it שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, לא קדשו הלחם,
lo kidshu halechem, the bread does not become קדוש kadosh because and
again would not become פסול if it was brought out of the
מקדש etc. Okay, so anyway you see there it's exactly the same.
Bread is associated with the שלמים shelamim even when something else exists,
when there's another קרבן.
So that's why the other ones aren't מעכב maakve.
essentially. And that's why the others are not מעכב. So that was
basically the answer. Alright I guess we'll have to end here so
unfortunately we're still going to be a little behind, hopefully we will
catch up soon.
Tomorrow when?
Tomorrow
night.